# ALEXANDER CURRAN

E - aml.curran@gmail.com W - www.amlcurran.co.uk

#### **ABOUT ME**

A highly experienced and product-focused engineering leader who has delivered many multi-million pound projects over 10 years. Proficient in both line managing and technical leadership, with a keen interest in developing the careers of others and sharing knowledge learnt from multiple industries and all company sizes, from pre-Series A startups to large corporations.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Engineering Manager, The Body Coach — March 2022-Jan 2023

- > Engineering manager of the Get Moving team (mission was focused on user install to first 30 days).
- > Line management of 4 engineers across Android and iOS. Responsible for the delivery of an additional 2 agency developers whilst facilitating their roll-off from the project.
- > Led project planning and delivery of multiple projects including Easy Start, In-app Motivational Messaging, and an A/B test on the paywall. Stepped in for Product Management when the role was vacated.
- > Implemented a reconfiguration of the existing separate Android and iOS teams into two crossfunctional mission-based teams.
- > Made redundant as part of a restructure.

# Principal Engineer, Freetrade — October 2019-March 2022

- > Principal Engineer on the Discover and Insights team and Onboarding team.
- > Delivered multiple projects including SIPP accounts, launching in the EU, Freetrade Plus, and fractional trading, all contributing to significant uplift in revenue and company OKRs.
- > Technical lead for the SIPPs project & EU onboarding, managing stakeholders, synchronising multiple teams' deliveries and communicating project progression.
- Developed the interview and hiring strategy for mobile across six teams growing the mobile team from 2 to 10 in 6 months. Acted as a consultant to EMs without mobile skillsets to develop the careers of their reports.
- > Created a strategy for mobile in the company including training backend-focused engineers in mobile, and building a design system, and breaking down monolithic codebases.
- Delivered Freetrade on iPad and Dark Mode as 20% time projects, both of which were well-received by customers.

# Engineering Manager & Project Lead, Novoda — March 2016-October 2019 Software Craftsman, Novoda — March 2015-March 2016

- > Line manager for 6 developers, responsible for performance reviews and goal setting.
- > Project lead & principle engineer for iOS, Android, and dual-platform projects with clients including ImmobilienScout24, AutoScout24, myBlu, and Oetker Digital.
- > Built and ran multiple workshops for clients and internal developers to fill identified skills gaps.
- > Mentored junior members of the team and the company to forward their careers.

> Responsible for promoting multi-platform development in the company, including a fully multi-platform project delivered, and up-skilling multiple developers to become proficient in other platforms.

# Software Engineer, BBC — July 2014-March 2015

# Junior Software Engineer, BBC — Aug 2013-July 2014

- > Worked on the Mobile Core Engineering team (included working with mobile iPlayer and iPlayer Radio).
- > Delivered Chromecast for BBC iPlayer and BBC Sport in collaboration with Google.
- > Worked multi-platform on iOS and Android in an agile environment.

# **Developer (self-employed)** — 2009-present

- > Android and iOS app developer; mostly scientific or developer-focused apps.
- > Current project is a dual-platform app to make regularly giving to charity easier.
- > Active open-source projects available on <u>Github</u>, apps on <u>Google Play</u>.

# **SKILLS AND TECHNICAL INTERESTS**

- > Excellent knowledge of Java, Objective-C, Swift, Kotlin, and ReactiveX.
- > Proficient with many third party technologies e.g. Firebase and GCP, A/B testing mechanisms and theory
- > Good knowledge of TypeScript; working knowledge of Javascript, React, Node.js, and Flutter,.
- > 12 years experience of Android development; 10 years of iOS; 4 with Node.js.
- > 10 years experience with software best practices & TDD; confident with unit, UI, and integration testing.
- > Keen interest in unified mobile development, including code transpilation and mixed platform pairing.
- > Confident in running and maintaining a cross-functional engineering team, with experience in product management lifecycles as well.
- > Responsible for client relations as part of the team, including stakeholder management and ensuring the development team has all they require to deliver a high-quality product.

### **EDUCATION**

# University of Oxford — 2009-2013

> First Class degree, Chemistry (Masters), Masters year on computational chemical analysis.

# The College of Richard Collyer — 2007-2009

# **ACTIVITIES**

#### **Presentations and demos**

- Talks at meet-ups and conferences (including Swift.berlin, Droidcon Paris). Ran the tutorial session "Spring cleaning your app" at <a href="RWDevCon 2018">RWDevCon 2018</a> and a talk about Real-time Apps at NSSpain 2021.
- > Mentor and facilitator as part of Codebar Berlin and London which supports underrepresented people getting into programming.
- > Frequently present internal presentations and run internal katas about clean code topics and new technologies. Keen blogger around code smells and refactoring.

### **Recreational activities**

- > Keen cook, baker, and mixologist.
- > Interest in crafts including pottery, soap and candle-making, and mixed-media art.